<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Otwarcia on Otwarcia Szachowe</title>
    <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Otwarcia on Otwarcia Szachowe</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Adelaide Counter Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/1/</guid>
      <description>When white plays the King’s Gambit they are usually looking to give up material and then have the initiative for the early part of the game. This defense turns the tables on white and gives black multiple attacking lines and control of the center. White has to be careful because if they don’t play properly there are many traps they can fall into. Below are different options they have after 3…f5.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Albin Counter-Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/2/</guid>
      <description>The Albin Counter-Gambit is a hyper aggressive defense for black against the ever so popular queens gambit from white.
Black gives up his pawn on e5 so that his d pawn can be nicely placed on d4. This pawn is a huge thorn in the side of white and there are many trap that come from the Albin Counter-Gambit that white has to be on the lookout for. One of the most common traps in the Albin Counter-Gambit is the Lasker Trap which punishes white if he tries to attack the pawn on d4 with e3.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alekhine Defense</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/3/</guid>
      <description>e4 Nf6
Black looks to allow white to chase his knight all over the board with tempo gaining pawn moves that will control the center of the board. In exchange for the center control, black will look to undermine the overextended pawns from white.
The one thing black must always remember is that after his knight has been chased around he no longer can play passively and instead needs to attack the center that white has built up or he will be crushed by the pressure white can build up.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Belgrade Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/4/</guid>
      <description>The Belgrade Gambit is an aggressive line that derives from the Scotch Four Knights Game:
White’s most common move after 4…exd4 is to recapture with 5. Nxd4 but Nd5 allows white to transition into the Belgrade Gambit. As with many less known gambits, the Belgrade gets much of its advantage from your opponent not being familiar with how to play correctly as black. The good thing about this variation is that if you play 1.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benoni Defense</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/5/</guid>
      <description>The Benoni Defense is a very aggressive line that black can play to counter the very common open by white d4. While many defenses against the queen pawn opening are closed and drawish, the Benoni Defense gives black many opportunities to not only equalize the position, but also to gain an advantage and play for the win.
In the Modern Benoni Defense, the main focus of the game is white’s center control of the light squares with its key pawn on d5 and black’s control of the center from the dark squares.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bird’s Opening</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/6/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/6/</guid>
      <description>The Bird’s Opening is the 6th most popular opening and is a very aggressive opening. White starts out weakening his king side and starts a flank attack on the center with his f pawn. This opening is not used in lots of top level play but some of the most beautiful games in chess history have been played using the Bird’s Opening.\
f4
After black defends with d5 the game will transpose into a reverse of the Dutch defense, where white opens with d4 and black responds with f5.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bishop’s Opening</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/7/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/7/</guid>
      <description>The Bishop’s Opening is one of the oldest openings in chess but has fallen out of favor recently. It starts with the moves:
White decides to develop the light square bishop before bringing the knight to f3. The three main responses from black are 2…Nf6, 2…Nc6, and 2…Bc5. White has good chances against each of these lines and can fall into more popular opening variations if they choose. After 3. d4 exd4 4.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blackmar-Diemer Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/8/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/8/</guid>
      <description>The Blackmar-Diemer Gambit is one of the most ambitious attempts for white to gain a developmental advantage.
From the second move white looks to give away his king’s pawn. Although many top GM’s find this to be unsound, many club level players have great success with it and if you are a very aggressive player I recommend playing it from time to time.
After white gives gambit’s his pawn he then looks to develop his knight to c3, followed by playing f3.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bogo Indian Defense</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/9/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/9/</guid>
      <description>The Bogo Indian Defense is a chess opening that arrives after the starting moves:
Many players with the white pieces will choose the third move Nf3 instead of Nc3 because they want to avoid the Nimzo Indian Defense. Black has multiple options after Nf3 but Bb4+ is a common move seen at all levels of play.
White has three primary options after Bb4+. 4. Nc3, Nbd2, Bd2.
Nc3 tends to go down a Nimzo-Indian Defense line.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Budapest Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/10/</guid>
      <description>The Budapest Gambit is one of the least common gambits but still offers black a lot of interesting play. In the main line for example, white can easily fall into a trap that ends in checkmate very early in the game.
In the second move, black looks to give up his pawn on e5 but then starts to develop of his pieces to add pressure on the e5 pawn. White will be unable to hold onto the extra pawn and therefore many times will just give back the pawn and continue to develop pieces and not worry about the pawn advantage.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calabrese Countergambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/11/</guid>
      <description>The Italian Game is white’s effort to quickly develop his light square bishop and dominate the center of the board. The Calabrese Countergambit is black’s way of giving up his f-pawn to completely thwart all of white’s game plan. The more aggressive white tries to be in the opening the more potential traps he can fall into.
Black usually ends up with a very strong center while white’s pieces struggle to find great squares to develop.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caro-Kann</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/12/</guid>
      <description>The Caro-Kann Defense is one of the most popular openings in response to the King’s Pawn Opening.\
e4 c6
Black responds with 1….c6 with the idea of thrusting forward with d5 on the next move, attacking the white central pawn on e4. The Caro-Kann Defense is one of the few defenses in chess where black can reach equality in the main line and many people would consider black to have a better position, especially in the end game when the main line is played out.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colorado Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/13/</guid>
      <description>The Colorado Gambit is an aggressive line in the Nimzowitsch Defence. Black looks to weaken his king side pawn structure in exchange for some deadly attacks against white. This is a solid opening for black but usually works best as a surprise opening against a player that hasn’t studied all of the lines.
White must play carefully as there are many traps and dangerous lines that black can play. Unlike other gambits, black would prefer that white not take the pawn on f5.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Danish Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/14/</guid>
      <description>The Danish Gambit is one of the most aggressive openings as white will look to sacrifice two pawns for quick development and the attack.
Many times you will see games with the Danish Opening last less than 20 moves as white will either breakthrough and checkmate the king early on or white will fail miserably and be left in shambles.
If accepted, white will have a strong bishop pair developed staring down at the black’s king side while black will have none of his pieces developed.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dutch Defense</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/15/</guid>
      <description>The Dutch Defense is a very active defense in chess against the Queen pawn opening.\
d4 f5
Black looks to control the e4-square while completely unbalancing the position. Later on in the chess game, black will look to future his attack on white’s kingside. One of the key concepts is that the weak f7 square that black has becomes even more a target for white and many times white will focus exclusively on targeting this weakness.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elephant Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/16/</guid>
      <description>The Elephant Gambit is an uncommon gambit that arrives after the starting moves:
White can take either of the pawns on e5 or d5. Both of the pawns have the own unique challenges.
If white takes on d5, then black can retake with the Queen but falls in development after Nc3 from white. Taking the pawn on e5 with Nxe5 is also viable but leaves the board state open for lots of attacking lines for black.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>English Opening</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/17/</guid>
      <description>The English opening is the 4th most common opening for white. Although the English has its own style, the opening is very flexible and many times transposes into other opening lines. The objective of the opening is to apply pressure on the center d5 square without committing the queen pawn or the king pawn. Since the move is a flank move many players like the English because of its hypermodern style of play (using pieces from the sides along with minor pieces to apply pressure and control the center).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evans Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/18/</guid>
      <description>The Evans Gambit is an aggressive variation of the Giuoco Piano. For those players that like to play the Giuoco Piano I highly recommend playing the Evan’s Gambit.
Much like other gambits, the Evan’s Gambit gives up an early pawn in exchange for rapid development and a lead in center control. White actually scores better with the Evan’s Gambit than not playing the gambit and following the main lines of the Giuoco Piano which is why I recommend playing it.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fajarowicz Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/19/</guid>
      <description>Welcome chess enthusiasts! excited to bring you insights into a particularly sneaky line in chess openings – the Fajarowicz variation. This cunning tactic diverges from the conventional paths of the Budapest defense, and today we’ll unravel its mysteries.
At its core, the Fajarowicz variation delves into psychological warfare, laying out an intricate network of traps that can snare even the most vigilant opponents. Let’s lay down the sequence leading to it:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Falkbeer Counter-Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/20/</guid>
      <description>The Falkbeer Counter-Gambit is one of the most aggressive openings for black. It is a direct counter attack against the King’s Gambit of white.
One of the great things about this counter is that it destroys all the lines that a king’s gambit player may have planned on using. There are also lots of traps that white will have to look out for as his king is very exposed even after the second move.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>French Defense</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/21/</guid>
      <description>The French Defense is a sharp counterattacking weapon against white’s King Pawn opening.\
e4 e6
From black’s first move, he looks to block the a2-g8 diagonal which is usually a big weakness for black and prepares to take control of the light squares in the center after 2.d5. Some of the greatest players of all time have had a hard time playing against the French Defense because it plays so much differently than a normal black defense.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fried Liver Attack</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/22/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/22/</guid>
      <description>The Fried Liver Attack is one of the most aggressive openings from white as you will be sacrificing one of your minor pieces very early in the game.
This aggressive attack starts from the Italian game and will play out if black chooses to defend with the two knights defense (as shown in the picture). If black chooses Bc5 instead of the two knights defense I recommend the Evan’s Gambit, since the fried liver attack will no longer work.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Giuoco Piano</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/23/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/23/</guid>
      <description>The Giuoco Piano is said to be the oldest opening recorded in chess. Instead of developing the bishop to b5, white instead attacks the center and aims at the weak f7 square. After black responds bishop to c5 you see the tension building up in the center of the board.
The opening has been called the “quiet game” but for anyone who has played this opening, after the initial build up in the center, the Giuoco Piano becomes anything but quiet.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grob Attack</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/24/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/24/</guid>
      <description>The Grob Attack is not a common opening and many people think of it as one of white’s weakest opening choices because it doesn’t attack the center of the board and it weakens the king’s safety. It begins with the move:\
g4
While this isn’t the strongest move from white there are still some interest lines that white can go down to put black in a tough spot. Black will normally respond to the Grob Attack with one of the following:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grunfeld Defense</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/25/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/25/</guid>
      <description>The Grunfeld Defense is a hypermodern defense, meaning that it doesn’t try to control the center early on with his pawns. Instead black tries to attack the center with this minor pieces from the sides and then once the foundation is in place, then looks to undermine the center control that white usually has.
There are three main lines in the Grunfeld Defense. The exchange variation is the main line and is what most players study for when approaching the Grunfeld Defense.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Halloween Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/26/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/26/</guid>
      <description>The Halloween Gambit, or the Muller-Schulze Gambit derives from the Four Knights Game but then takes on a very aggressive approach as white sacrifices a knight for a pawn with the hopes of controlling the center with white’s pawns. White hopes to do this by driving back black’s knights while pushing forward his pawns.
Even though black will be retreating his knights, black has more than enough compensation for white’s temporary advancement in the center.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Icelandic Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/27/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/27/</guid>
      <description>The Icelandic Gambit is an aggressive alternative to the Scandinavian Defense. Instead of taking the pawn on d5, black looks to give up the material in exchange for developmental lead and a semi-open file for his queen.
White has to be very careful as the Icelandic Gambit has many different traps that one can fall into. Black has all of his pieces positioned nicely while white has none of his pieces developed and a pawn structure that lacks substance going into an end game.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Italian Game</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/28/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/28/</guid>
      <description>The Italian Game is one of the oldest openings in chess. After 1. e4 e5 2. Nf3 Nc6 white looks to centralize more material by bringing his bishop to c4. While this is a very active square early on, this opening can many times become a very quiet and slow game. Both sides of the board look to stabilize without trading off any material.
The good news is that there are many aggressive variations that white can play to open the game up.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jerome Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/29/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/29/</guid>
      <description>The Jerome Gambit is an extremely aggressive opening that usually derives from the Giuoco Piano. White sacrifices both his king side bishop and knight in exchange for an exposed king and the possibility of an aggressive attack. Moves usually start with:
White usually continues with Qh5+. This gets the most important piece into the attack early and leaves black with the most possibilities to blunder. If black moves Ke7 or f6 then white is going to have a fairly easy game.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>King’s Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/30/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/30/</guid>
      <description>The King’s Gambit is one of the oldest openings in chess and for good reason. The possibilities the opening presents have intrigued the greatest chess minds for years including greats such as Spassky, Tal, and Fischer. White, on the second move challenges black’s center and begins an attack at the black kingside.
Black can accept or decline the gambit. Most players choose to accept the gambit and try to counterattack the now semi-exposed king side of white.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kings Indian Defense</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/31/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/31/</guid>
      <description>The Kings Indian Defense is one of the most solid defenses in chess. Black builds an extremely strong defense around his king and then looks to counter attack depending on where white’s structure is weak.
Play normally starts in the Kings Indian Defense with the moves:
This defense is a hypermodern idea that allows white to control the center of the board early on while black looks to develop his minor pieces early on and move his pawns towards the center later on in the game.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Larsens Opening</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/32/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/32/</guid>
      <description>Larsens Opening is a change of pace from the typical openings where white looks to control the center of the board with this d and e pawns. Instead white will play his bishop to b2 and control the dark square diagonal which will put pressure on black’s king side.
This is not an aggressive opening but does give white many favorable positions and also is poorly prepared for by black.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Latvian Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/33/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/33/</guid>
      <description>The Latvian Gambit is a very aggressive opening defense for black against one of the more common openings for white. This opening is not seen much at master level chess as most masters refuse to give up material early on in a game. Below master level play there are strong advocates of the Latvian Gambit and I personally enjoy the possibilities that arise from this opening.
What makes this is such an interesting opening is that white does not have many good moves besides accepting the gambit.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Locock Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/34/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/34/</guid>
      <description>The Locock Gambit is a very aggressive line in the Philidor Defense and starts with the moves:
The Philidor Defense is generally pretty passive. When you start out with e5 and d6 you are playing for a very long game by building up a strong pawn structure. This can be very frustrating for many players starting out with e4 because they are looking for an aggressive start.
With the Locock Gambit, white is able to regain the initiative and play a very aggressive line.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lolli Attack</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/35/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/35/</guid>
      <description>The Lolli Attack is an aggressive opening for white in the Italian game when black defends with the two knights defense. Instead of immediately sacrificing the knight on f7, white instead plays d4, sacrificing another pawn and then castling kingside.
This is very similar to the Fried Liver Attack, but castling on the kingside gives white another powerful piece, the rook, involved into the attack. Regardless of how black defends, white will look to sacrifice his knight on f7 and the start the assault against the black king.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>London System</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/36/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/36/</guid>
      <description>The London System is a great chess opening for beginning chess players. It quickly develops the dark square bishop which is a very underutilized minor piece for white.
The opening doesn’t start out aggressive, and many times ends in a closed game, but it gives white lots of options and is very useful is stopping black from any counterattack.
The London System is extremely good against the King’s Indian Defense systems as black becomes cramped and is left with little room to do anything.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matinovsky Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/37/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/37/</guid>
      <description>The Matinovsky Gambit is an aggressive line by black in the Owen’s Defense. It starts with the moves:
Black looks to give up the f pawn in exchange for an activated light squared bishop. Black can immediately take on g2 and threaten the h1 rook. If white plays correctly the rook on h1 will stay safe and should have a very good game. White should always accept the gambit but must make sure they are familiar with the opening or things can turn quickly in black’s favor.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Muzio Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/38/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/38/</guid>
      <description>The Muzio Gambit is one of the most aggressive lines in the already aggressive King’s Gambit.
Instead of counter attacking with the knight on f3, white gives that knight up in exchange for a massive attack with his bishop, queen and castled king. Black is up in material but has a weakened king side and no developed pieces.
There are numerous traps that black can fall into and it is extremely difficult to avoid all of them</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nakhmanson Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/39/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/39/</guid>
      <description>For this overview we will be looking the accepted lines after 6…dxc3 7. Bxf7 Kxf7 8. Qd5+. In this line white has given up two pawns, a knight, and now a bishop all for the thrill of a devastating attack on the black king. In this position the black king has to move. We will cover each of the moves for the king. This is not a great move for black.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nimzo Indian Defense</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/40/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/40/</guid>
      <description>The Nimzo Indian Defense is an extremely solid defense that is seen at all levels of play. Many players playing as white will try different variations to try to avoid going into the Nimzo Indian Defense lines.
Black looks to double up the pawns on the c-file in exchange for his dark square bishop. With the knight on c3 the key defender of the e4 square, black really starts to focus his energy on controlling the e4 and the light squares.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Petrov Defense</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/41/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/41/</guid>
      <description>The Petrov Defense, sometimes referred to as the Russian game is one of the more popular games with GMs because of its generally drawish tendencies. Many other players prefer to play the Petrov Defense so that they can avoid the lines of the Ruy Lopez, the Italian Game and the Scotch Game. For those players that like to play e5 but don’t like the normal defenses, then this might be a good alternative.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Philidor Defense</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/42/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/42/</guid>
      <description>The Philidor Defense is an alternative move to the more common 2…Nc6 move from black. While very solid, it is extremely passive and thought to be a weaker option to Nc6. Because of this, it is rare to see at high level play.
At lower levels of chess and even club levels the Philidor Defense is common so even if you don’t intend to play it yourself it’s always important to understand how to play against it.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pirc Defense</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/43/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/43/</guid>
      <description>The Pirc Defense is a hypermodern defense, meaning that it doesn’t try to control the center early on with his pawns. Instead black tries to attack the center with this minor pieces from the sides and then once the foundation is in place, then looks to undermine the center control that white usually has.
There are two main attacks that white has to play against the Pirc Defense. The Austrian Attack is the most aggressive as white pushes his f pawn to f4, exposing a weakness on his king side but putting added pressure on the king side of black.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ponziani Opening</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/44/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/44/</guid>
      <description>The ponziani opening begins with the moves
White looks to build up a support for a later push of d4, controlling the dark squares in the center of the board.
Many chess players find c3 to be inferior to both the Ruy Lopez, 3. Bb5 and the Italian Game 3. Bc4. While I will agree that the Ponziani is not seen at the GM level often and is thought to be equal for black, there still is much theory to be explored in the opening and white has many opportunities to come out far ahead if black is not well prepared.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Queens Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/45/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/45/</guid>
      <description>The objective of the queen’s gambit is to temporarily sacrifice a pawn to gain control of the center of the board.
If black accepts the gambit 2…dxc4 white should reply 3. e3 which not only gives the d4 pawn an extra defender but also frees up the bishop to attack and regain the pawn. Black will have a hard time holding onto the pawn after 3…b5 4. a4 c6 5. axb5 cxb5 6.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Queens Indian Defense</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/46/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/46/</guid>
      <description>The Queen’s Indian Defense is an extremely solid hypermodern defense against the d4 opening from white. It usually arises if white chooses to avoid the Nimzo-Indian defense by bringing his knight to c3 and instead opts to first bring his knight to f3.
Black prepares to fiachetto his light square bishop and try to take control over both the center light squares as well as the long diagonal.
White has a few options but usually will opt for g3, challenging the long diagonal by fianchettoing his own bishop to g2.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reti Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/47/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/47/</guid>
      <description>The Reti Gambit is an aggressive approach to attack the French Defense and it starts with the moves:
The e6 move signals the French Defense and play usually continues:
White gives up the e4 pawn for rapid development on the queen side of the board and the ability to keep the board wide open. As white playing e4, the French Defense is something many players don’t want to see and this opening gives white multiple variations to continue the aggressive nature of an e4 opening while thwarting many of the ideas a typical French Defense player has.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reti Opening</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/48/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/48/</guid>
      <description>The Reti Opening has at times been referred to as the Opening of the Future. It is called this because of how easy it is to transpose into a variety of different opening lines. Many players have a very defined defense as black but against the Reti, black is forced to almost wait and see which opening line white will take. Some of the main opening lines that the Reti will transpose into are the Queen’s Gambit, the English, the Ruy Lopez, or the King’s Indian Attack.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ruy Lopez</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/49/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/49/</guid>
      <description>The Ruy Lopez is the cornerstone of classical play in chess. There are probably more variations for the Ruy Lopez than any other opening. With the common use of the double king’s pawn opening (1.e4 e5), the Ruy Lopez is one of the most played openings that any chess player will come across. It’s almost imperative that any chess player study some of the more popular defenses against the Ruy Lopez and understand some of the key concepts of the opening.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scandinavian Defense</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/50/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/50/</guid>
      <description>The Scandinavian Defense is one of the oldest recorded openings in chess. From the very first move, black looks to undermine the center control of white after the common e4 move by white.\
e4 d5
Nine times out of ten white will capture the pawn on d5 and I recommend that you spend the majority of your time learning the Scandinavian Defense, assuming that white captures the pawn on d5.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scotch Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/51/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/51/</guid>
      <description>There are a few ways to offer a gambit as white in the Scotch Game. The most common, and one that we will focus on this page, is white playing Bc4 instead of taking with his knight on d4.
This does many different things but it delays the middle control of the board with the knight and pawn in exchange for a very powerful bishop that eyes down on the f7 pawn from black.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scotch Game</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/52/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/52/</guid>
      <description>The Scotch Game has recently regained popularity as many top level players have used it as a surprise against players who are well equipped to face the Ruy Lopez. The Scotch is very similar to the Center Game where d4 opens up lines for development and also gives white early center control. In the Scotch Game, black will be able to develop easy and white should look to take advantage of its special and center control.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semi-Slav</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/53/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/53/</guid>
      <description>The Semi-Slav Defense is one of the most popular defenses for black against the Queen’s Gambit line from white. This opening is seen at all levels of chess competition and is often seen as one of the most sound defenses at top level play.
Black spends most of the time in the Semi-Slav developing pawns and pieces to control the light squares in the middle of the board. It differs from the Slav opening in that the light square bishop on c8 is not developed before the pawn structure is formed with e6.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sicilian Defense</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/54/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/54/</guid>
      <description>The Sicilian Defense is the most popular defense against white’s opening 1.e4 and is used extensively at top level play. It is a very aggressive defense and immediately stakes claim at the center, denying white the double pawns on e4 and d4. Many chess champions actually prefer to start with 1.d4 because of how well the Sicilian Defense plays against 1.e4.
Eventually the c-pawn of black is usually exchanged, opening the semi-open c file for black to bring his queen or rook to and add pressure to the queen side attack.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Slav Defense</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/55/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/55/</guid>
      <description>The Slav Defense is one of the most popular openings with GM’s. This is for two reasons. The first is that it is one of the most solid lines to play against the Queens Gambit and with the Queens Gambit being a regular opening at high level play, many top players have become fans of this opening.
The Slav also allows for lots of different variations so those players that like to be creative and don’t like to play the same variation every game will really enjoy the Slav Defense because it offers just that.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Slav Geller Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/56/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/56/</guid>
      <description>Welcome chess enthusiasts! I’ve got a fascinating treat for you: the Slav Geller Gambit. This is an opening that packs a punch and can set your opponent on their heels if they’re not careful.
Before we dive into the waters of the Geller Gambit, let’s set the baseline. Picture the classic Queen’s Gambit. White moves 1.d4, asserting control in the center, and then follows up with 2.c4. This demands a response, and here’s where Black counters with the steadfast Slav Defense by playing 2…c6.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Smith Morra Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/57/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/57/</guid>
      <description>The Smith Morra Gambit is a sharp and aggressive line against the Sicilian Defense from black. If you play e4 as white for any length of time you probably run into the Sicilian Defense quite often.
This gambit is only for very aggressive players as are most gambits. White looks to not only take black out of the normal Sicilian lines but also looks to use the advantage in development to overwhelm the black king.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stafford Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/58/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/58/</guid>
      <description>The accepted line continues with:
4. Nxc6 dxc6
Black is giving up a pawn to open up the center for both bishops and queen to freely attack. White will normally continue with d4, d3, or Nc3. All of these have many traps that white can fall into which makes this opening so dangerous.
With the e-pawn under attack it makes sense for white to push forward and attack the knight on f6.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tennison Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/59/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/59/</guid>
      <description>The Tennison Gambit is an aggressive line against the Scandinavian defense that starts with the moves:
Black is almost always going to capture the pawn on e4 and white should respond with Ng5. This puts black in an interesting position. If black tries to hold onto the pawn advantage there are many lines where black will forfeit his position or even the lead in material.
If black does not hold onto the material, white can recapture and have a very good development in the game.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Alien Gambit Trap</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/60/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/60/</guid>
      <description>Welcome back, chess aficionados! We’re diving into an intriguing new opening that’s making waves in the chess community: the Alien Gambit. This fresh strategy turns the tables on Caro-Kann players and can lead to some pretty exciting complications early in the game.
The dance begins with the classic 1.e4. In response, Black sets the stage for the Caro-Kann, steering the pawn to c6. The plan? To challenge White’s central dominance with …d5.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Three Knights Game</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/61/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/61/</guid>
      <description>Greetings, chess enthusiasts! Bringing you insights from the chess realm. We’ll delve into the intriguing world of the Three Knights Game — a variation that chess aficionados might mix up with its close relative, the Four Knights Game.
“Three Knights may tread lightly at first, but tread smartly and the game is yours to command.” – A Chess Sage
To wrap up, dear reader, the Three Knights Game isn’t just another chess opening.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Traxler Counter Attack</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/62/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/62/</guid>
      <description>The Traxler counter attack derives from the two knights defense from black after white develops into the Italian game.
After white moves his knight to g5, attacking the weakened f7 square, black counter attacks with Bc5, disregarding his own safety for a lethal attack on white’s king side.
If white captures the pawn on f7 with his knight, forking the queen and the rook, black can start the counter attack with Bxf2.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Urusov Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/63/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/63/</guid>
      <description>The Urusov Gambit is an aggressive line in the Bishop’s opening that starts with the moves:
Instead of playing the normal Nc3 or Nf3, white looks to add pressure to the center of the board with d4 and open up more lanes for white’s remaining pieces to get involved into the attack. Black has two responses. Black taking on e4 with his knight is definitely a worse move. White can play dxe5 and then start to attack the knight on e4.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vienna Game</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/64/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/64/</guid>
      <description>The Vienna Game is one of the most fundamentally sound openings in chess. It follows all of the basic opening principles and allows for creativity for both aggressive and non-aggressive players.
Black has three main options to respond to the Vienna Game. They are 2….Nf6, 2….Bc5, 2…..Nc6. Each response from black opens up the door for white to choose how the game will proceed.
White can play a quiet game, simply developing minor pieces towards the middle of the board and try to stay ahead in time and space, or white can play a gambit with f4, transposing into various King’s Gambit lines.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wing Gambit</title>
      <link>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/65/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:54:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bartix998a.github.io/otwarcia/65/</guid>
      <description>The Wing Gambit can be found in multiple opening lines. This page is specifically looking at the Wing Gambit in the Sicilian Defense. It starts with the moves:
White looks to give up the b pawn in exchange for the removal of black’s dangerous c pawn in the Sicilian Defense. Usually black will take the pawn on b4 and white will continue with a3.
While many gambits give a side a strong attack, an extra tempo, or a better position, the Wing Gambit is difficult to play as White and have a strong game.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
